"How to Get Rid of Garlic Breath"
Approximately
one in three people
suffer from halitosis-
bad breath.
What can we do about it?
I've got videos
on tongue cleaning, gum chewing,
and the best mouthwash.
Population studies suggest
that those who eat
fewer fruits and vegetables
may be at higher risk,
but there are a lot of things
associated with worse diets
that are also linked
to halitosis,
though the fruit
and vegetable link
seemed to remain
even after controlling
for these other factors.
It works in dogs.
Vegetable chew toys
seem to help,
but what about people?
There's a compound found
in cruciferous vegetables
that can effectively eliminate
the volatile sulfur compounds
like the rotten egg gas
hydrogen sulfide.
These are the foul gases
that cause bad breath
produced mainly
from the breakdown
of sulfur-containing
amino acids
concentrated in animal protein-
cysteine and methionine.
The cruciferous compound gloms
onto the sulfur compound
and prevents it
from going gaseous;
whereas peppermint,
spearmint, wintergreen,
and many of the flavors
in breath mints and chewing gum
didn't actually treat the cause,
and just kind of have
a masking effect.
Whereas something
like broccoli chewing gum
might help
at least temporarily,
but why not just eat broccoli
instead?
Researchers have tried
using a compound
that clears cysteine
from the tongue
for those who don't just want
to try to cut down on casein
and other animal proteins
that are concentrated in it.
The compound they used
is derived from kiwi fruit,
so can you just eat kiwis
instead?
No word on halitosis,
but twice daily kiwi fruit
consumption for two months
showed significant improvements
in gingivitis, plaque,
and gum disease.
Of course, not all fruits
are going to be beneficial.
Durian fruit may give rise
to the most profound bad breath
because the fruit itself
stinks to high heaven,
as many of you will remember
from my harrowing experience
with it in medical school
that I sheepishly related
in my book How Not to Die.
And the vegetable
that comes to mind
when you think bad breath
is garlic.
Is there anything you can do
to deodorize garlic breath
using different kinds of foods?
Well, you don't know
until you put it to the test.
After giving people
some garlic,
they tried whey protein,
lemon juice, green tea,
chlorophyll, 7UP soda,
a raw pink lady apple,
a cooked apple, parsley,
spinach, and mint leaves.
Anyone want to take a guess
as to which worked best?
Parsley, spinach,
and mint treatments
were effective
in the deodorization
of garlic breath
stinky compounds.
They're all green,
so they wondered
if it was the chlorophyll,
and it turned out, nope,
chlorophyll alone didn't help.
Here are the graphs.
There are four
stinky garlic compounds.
If you don't do anything
after the garlic,
the stench goes away
on its own.
And taking chlorophyll didn't
seem to change that at all,
but parsley, spinach,
and mint did,
starting almost immediately.
What do we think was going on?
Well, raw apples worked better
than cooked apples,
which are basically
the same food
except for the enzymes
being destroyed by heating,
so maybe there's
some enzymatic deodorization.
Here's the data.
And, yes, raw worked better
than cooked,
but cooked still worked
better than nothing,
and so did the lemon juice
and green tea,
even though they didn't have
any active enzymes
since they were
both pasteurized.
Here's the beverages data.
The whey protein in water
didn't seem to help at all,
even compared with the soda,
though green tea and lemon
appeared to do better.
Maybe the acidic pH
was involved
in the deodorization
from the lemon juice
and soft drink
breath experiments,
since they used
a sour lemon-lime soft drink.
Garlic breath volatiles
(allyl methyl disulfide,
diallyl disulfide,
allyl mercaptan)
were significantly reduced
by parsley, spinach, mint,
raw and microwaved apple,
soft drink, green tea,
and lemon juice treatments
in comparison to water
(the control)
but were not reduced
by chlorophyll
and whey protein treatments.
And perhaps
the polyphenol phytonutrients
were the active ingredient
in green tea.
With consumption
of full-flavor garlic,
it is not yet possible
to completely avoid
malodorous breath associated
with garlic consumption,
but there are some chasers
that may help you
bring it down a notch.